

Alex Pliutau, Engineering Lead

Software Engineer with 10+ years of experience bringing products from concept to release in a variety of environments and companies. Organizational and leadership skills garnered from multiple supervisory positions, including but not limited to: mentoring, appropriate delegation, flat organizational communication, task assignment & assistance. Love challenges, clean code, concise documentation, clear communication and constructive feedback. My biggest strengths are APIs, Containers, Cloud, Web, Microservices. Currently I like to use Go to build scalable and fault tolerant backend systems.

Links

<u>Stackoverflow</u>

Youtube

<u>Github</u>

Linkedin

Blog

Employment History

Engineering Lead at Solsten, Berlin

January 2019 — Present

- Architected a Cloud-native backend for a company product from scratch using Microservices, Go, Kubernetes
- Manage, coach, and lead a team of 10+ engineers, including reviewing their performance and goals and providing ongoing professional development
- · Contributing to interviewing, hiring, and training new engineers
- Led the information security certification process for ISO27001, automated security best practices in Cloud

Engineering Manager at Wizeline, Ho Chi Minh City

May 2018 — September 2018

- Managed 10 engineers
- Delivered process improvements across the engineering department
- Connected with clients by presenting and explaining software architecture proposals
- Performed > 100 technical interviews
- Improved the interview process, by preparing new on-site challenges
- Running internal training programs

Senior Software Engineer at Wizeline, Ho Chi Minh City

March 2017 — May 2018

Lead a team of engineers to build Facebook Messenger Bot, using Node.js for API

- · Built a project utilizing Wit.ai for NLU
- Built Google Home Voice Bot with AWS Lambda and Serverless
- Built a facial recognition office assistant using Go and Tensorflow
- Held few internal and public tech talks: Microservices with Go, The Art of Git.

Senior Software Engineer at Lazada, Ho Chi Minh City

October 2014 — March 2017

- Lead software development subteam in DevOps team
- Helped the company to migrate a monoloth to microservices on Kubernetes
- Created a web and CLI project to create a new microservice based on a standard template, which automated the deployment, service registry and configuration
- Developed a company-wide data migration tool in Go based on golang-migrate open source project
- Technologies used: Golang, Javascript, Docker, Kubernetes, Beanstalkd, Jenkins, MySQL

Senior Fullstack Engineer at Tuffle, Minsk

November 2012 — September 2014

- Lead a team of 6 engineers to build a tech stack for a social network platform
- Selected appropriate libraries and open source technologies for project integration
- Deployed the solution to bare-metal servers using Ansible
- Technologies used: PHP, Javascript, MySQL, MongoDB, Memcached, Nginx

Software Engineer at iTechArt, Minsk

August 2010 — October 2012

- I was working in the Backend team providing services for clients
- At that time I mostly used PHP and it's frameworks such as Zend Framework
- Was working on security optimizations for web projects, protecting the system from SQL injections, CSRF, XSS

Education

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science, Belarusian State University of Informatics and Radioelectronics, Minsk

APIs

January 2007 — January 2012

Skills

Cloud-native applications

gRPC Web development

Infrastructure as Code CI/CD

Google Cloud AWS

Kubernetes Microservices

Go Python

Typescript Javascript

System Design Project Management

Training and Mentoring